howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
gymrutshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
today's guest is rob malda back in the
day
he was known by his slashdot handled
commander taco and he tells me he's
still known by that
uh he was the guy along with one of his
buddies who started the famous
website slash dot you know back in uh
you know way back yonder it was uh
absolutely must read when i was
a cto of thompson now thompson reuters
they say about 1999 onward
i checked it every day when i was ceo of
network solutions and we were involved
with the icann wars
it was again absolute must read so
interesting how i happened to invite rob
on the show
in fact i'd call it some synchronicity a
couple of weeks ago
i was talking with my friend peter wang
who's the ceo of anaconda the python
tools company about moderation systems
of the past and what they might have
with respect to lessons for the future
and i mentioned
uh then slash dot and i mentioned how it
had
had a very interesting and unusual
rating system going on
and uh frankly i said i had no idea
whether flash
dot still existed peter assured me that
it did
then last week i saw rob musing on
twitter about writing a history of
slashdot
and while i'm supposed to be on a
six-month break from social media
i think where am i now i guess i'm
halfway through month three
i still do one screen a week just to get
a
zeitgeist of the vibe on the nets so i
just happened to see that i guess some
one of my friends happened to like it or
share it or something so i
i said you know two signals in a
row
in seven days got to be something there
so i reached out to him said hey rob
hey you can start talking about the
history of slashdot here
so rob how you doing i am well
that's a good thing this craziest of all
years
so let me start with the obvious first
question
where the hell did the handle commander
taco come from
so commander taco is a reference to a
dave berry
quote uh he wrote a book i don't know
probably in the 80s
uh maybe 90s and it was like a joke
dating guide
and the commander taco was the name of a
restaurant that you should never take a
first date
now in my hometown it was quite common
to take a first date
to jack in the box at two o'clock in the
morning for the
nastiest greasiest tacos ever i guess we
didn't read that book
there you go about that so that's we're
gonna talk about slashdot today
so what how did it start what was the
deal what what the hell were you guys
doing when you launched it
yeah we didn't know either uh so
slashdot started uh
like let's say 1997 it grew out of uh
i was working at an ad agency as a
part-time job building websites
uh i was in college at the time and that
in 19 let's say 1995 1996 nobody knew
how to write html
and i hung out with graphic designers
and i was an engineer
and i hung out in irc chat rooms and
usenet message boards
and was writing what would in 2020
be commonly known as a blog but in 1996
1995 had no name it was just a home page
uh and all of those things just sort of
swirl together
and over the course of uh a couple of
years there
i built the slashdot thing cool
and uh as i recall the the
software that you ran on has always been
open source is that was that correct
i don't know if it's always been open
source but it was definitely open
sourced after
after a time the first couple of
versions of it were not anything
shippable
okay they were you know hodgepodged
pearl scripts duct taped together
uh but uh after a few years we
made a concerted effort to release the
whole platform as an open source package
and lots of websites uh in the
early early 90s ran it it was called
slash
there was a number of sites that were of
varying degrees of popularity that used
our code
uh although i don't think that any of
them
[Music]
really plumbed the depths the way we did
it wasn't really a useful application
for most people because
it was itself highly tuned for our
specific use case which was a pretty
large population
and a lot of the weird code that made it
difficult for noobs to
install was basically built around us
building a scalable platform both in
terms of the available hardware that we
had
like average folks didn't have you know
15 servers to host it on
but also we were constantly dealing with
trolls so
a lot of the code in the system was uh
the moderation system
uh and those were not the the system was
overly complex if you didn't have our
problems
yeah i know that feeling uh back in 2013
i
uh was part of a project where we put up
a community
system board that we thought was going
to get bigger than it did and we
foolishly
uh took a fork of the reddit uh source
code
oh you and it and had the same issue it
had you know
massive back end scaling potential which
we thought we were going to need
well guess what we missed that by two
orders of magnitude oh well
and so it was a disproportionate pain in
the ass
from a devops perspective and from an
operational perspective
uh but it was fun nonetheless and i
actually still have that code i know
it's no longer available
but so if anybody ever needs a copy of
the reddit source code from 2013
including a bunch of cool enhancements
let me know
i'll i'll keep that in mind should i
ever find a desire to build up another
site the code is not bad
but i would also say it is not good it's
somewhere in between if you know what i
mean
right i have a feeling that uh it was
developed uh
under not dissimilar circumstances from
my own
so uh that that's not really the ideal
way to
start an open source project and as far
as i know they never rewrote it it's
just
you can just see the uh you know it's
kind of like the ruins of troy 13 layers
of slag one on top of the other
so you started around 1997 when did you
start to build
you know significant traffic uh we
i guess i don't know how you define
significant we were we were
pretty big pretty fast uh but i guess
that's all relative
uh i was very active in the irc
community uh for the linux
uh space i was a open source developer i
was
writing code and contributing to various
platforms and my site
even before slashdot existed had a
certain percent a certain amount of
traffic
but you know uh that would be like you
know hundreds or thousands of users a
day so slashdot itself when it came out
when it started was just
me saying all of my stuff is here now uh
and it had thousands of people almost
immediately uh
but uh it grew to tens of thousands
uh in a few months uh and hundreds of
thousands
uh within within a year or two um
we were uh very fortunate uh
i can't i don't have a lot of advice in
terms of how you would grow such a thing
except for to do the right thing and
don't be dumb uh it seems like that's a
lesson that a lot of websites don't
really understand anymore but you know
yeah let's also be honest be the right
place at the right time right
any second man yeah exactly right and uh
as i said in the opener uh it was kind
of the must-read source for
serious biz tech nerds uh in the day
right uh
whenever there was some hack or some new
policy issue that it was arising
first place i went slashdot for uh for a
good five years there
uh we were i wouldn't say the only game
in town but we were
heading shoulders above the rest because
your other choices would be the
mainstream tech publications and they
were
they very much uh grew out of the
traditional print media so they had
they had a certain flavor to them uh i
wouldn't call them stale lame and boring
but uh i just did
uh other people might right i mean yeah
it was interesting and but then on the
other hand
eventually it started to fade i still
sort of recall
when i first noticed it fading it was
you know by this point i'd retired from
business in 2001 and
had reinvented myself as a scientist and
i was out at the santa fe institute
doing
uh research on agent-based evolutionary
artificial intelligence how about that
for a mouthful
but i still had some you know tech
investments and still advised if i was
on a few boards and what have you
remember something came up and i
immediately went to slashdot and said
slashdot should be the place to learn
about this but about 2003
and there was hardly anything there and
what was there was a little weak
and then i discovered ours technica and
that then became my kind of go-to place
around that time
yeah ours was ours was solid for a long
time there yeah
i would say slashdot held on uh its
relevance uh
up until uh the era of dig
and reddit uh uh once they started
achieving a certain amount of traction
slashdot lost uh some of its luster
uh but there was a lot going on uh and
the new uh more
uh i guess the more modern crowd-sourced
uh flavors became more popular uh
and along with that i think uh slashdot
began to gently set
into the sun well yes that happens
sometimes
anyway let's get to the point uh that uh
you know peter wang and i were talking
about
at least back in the day as i recall and
who knows maybe i'm getting senile but i
recall that you had a
rating system where people were selected
somehow
uh at in relatively low frequency to
rate the stories
uh was that is that correct did i
remember that right well
uh i might nitpick uh on your
terminology
uh slashdot was always a
the story selection process when you say
stories uh i think about the story
selection process
and i think you're trying to describe
the comment moderation process uh we
always took story submissions from
uh our users right in the
later eras uh in the later era the
2007 range let's say there was a voting
system where the community could
participate in the story selection
process
but within about a maybe a year in
change of slashdot's existence the
comment moderation system was
very much an active development and i
think that's probably the piece that uh
that most people think of when they
think about uh slashdot its role
uh in large scale discussion systems i
mean there weren't a lot of systems
in 1998 1999 that would
potentially have hundreds of active
contributors uh
posting uh within a few hours uh and
also allowed
uh anonymity within the context of the
platform
so our system uh was uh
uniquely evolved to deal with the
problems that we
saw yeah okay i think you're right yeah
now you know again this was a while ago
and i'm getting old god damn it
uh and so was the it was the uh
the comment moderation that you picked
people
it was not everybody got the vote people
were picked for short periods of time
like a couple of days
and and you had i don't know did you
have a limited number of votes i don't
even remember but
i still remember being selected several
times and taking it
seriously because it was a high-powered
signal you know unlike
a like on facebook or an update right on
reddit what you think of as a cheap
signal
if you got tapped uh with this limited
uh period uh franchise yeah actually
took it seriously
why don't you explain how that system
worked yeah scarcity
uh creates value uh the way that the
system generally worked is that uh
you had to be an active participant
within the community uh which i had a
number of different
metrics that i would measure to decide
if you were able to participate or not
one of the things was you got to read
the site and you can't read too much
so there was sort of a sweet spot you
had to read the page the site more than
a couple of times a day and you had to
read the site less than let's say
i'll pick a number 50 times a day if you
were that then we then the concern would
be that you were trying to game the
system and get points
uh intentionally and we absolutely had
to deal with that problem later on
but the system would basically dole out
eligibility tokens
if you happened to be if you fell within
the the window of people who were good
contributors during that time window and
when the system so basically
as users would post comments we would
push eligibility tokens into the system
and once uh enough comments had been in
the system we would pull whoever had the
most tokens
uh out of the pile uh and give them mod
points so that would actually amount to
uh you know a few hundred people a day
uh or maybe a few thousand people a day
depending on the era getting mod points
uh at which point uh the specifics would
vary
depending on whether you're talking
about 1998 or 2008 but
you'd get let's say five or ten points
and you were usually given 24
48 72 hours to spend them uh
at which point you would read the
comments and you would find the ones you
liked and you could choose to
send them up a point or down a point and
i mean at the core that's the whole
system i
we had uh scarcity uh which
created urgency uh and over time
we were able to identify
uh users who were bad actors and users
who were good actors
within the system and sort of uh adjust
some levers
to make sure that the right people were
getting the points at the right time and
the
the bad actors got weeded out of the
system and we were able to get to a
place where we were able to spend
we were able to generate a community
that could spend you know thousands of
points within the system a day
which was usually enough i i tried to
maintain a ratio of comment posts to
moderator activity
uh and that that that kind of was the
sweet spot whereas
today when you see a you know a tweet or
a
reddit post uh with uh with your likes
or whatever
uh that's essentially an infinite
resource you can have a tweet with uh
with 10 million likes on it
but the system the slashdot system was
designed uh to not actually have that
uh because i always felt that uh the
scarcity is what uh what made the system
kind of reliable yeah exactly i mean at
the time when i was most active on
slashdot i was the
ceo of a billion dollar company right my
time was precious
uh but when i got those little taps uh
you know i took it seriously and i
actually
uh said okay here's some significant
signal
in the community that i respect and so i
did it and i paid a lot of attention to
it
and so i think that was uh you know damn
clever design
uh the other thing that's nice about it
is it defeats some of the game
theoretical hacks
on open rating systems i mean uh
famously
reddit is where brigading got started
right it was i can still remember the
uh reddit says versus the anti-shit
reddit says
brigade wars when hundreds of people
would attack each other's posts and
upgrade them or down rate them etc
your system seemed pretty damn resilient
against brigading as an example
you know what's interesting is that uh i
said this earlier but
uh in the later naughties we developed a
system to rate stories
and uh to sort of leverage uh our
population in the story selection
process but i wasn't comfortable
simply flipping the switch and using a
model like a like a reddit or a dig
where
the community votes exclusively
determine the content content of the
homepage
and when that happened we
saw a lot of that brigading style
attacks
on this uh this new system which didn't
have the same scarcity of moderation
but i had designed that system
to avoid it rather than revealing for
example specific
uh integer values for
the posts uh i color coded them uh
so uh the color codes underneath the
hood
could represent uh any number they it
could be a million likes or it could be
seven
uh if it was the right seven uh but uh
or the right like if i moderated it up
that was worth more than you
because sorry jim you're a nice guy but
uh i you know i i know what i like and i
know what's going on slashdot
uh but uh the the system we've
absolutely had that brigading type
material
behavior in that system and that
the development of that of the the story
rating system
very much was influenced by the
successes that we had had with the
moderation system i was trying to find
a hybrid uh between the two between the
more public
uh reddit type systems uh which are
easily gameable
or relatively easily gameable uh and i
what i found actually is that
some of the worst offenders for the
brigading style tactics were actually
the publishers themselves
they would routinely
get into our system we called it the
fire hose they would get into the fire
hose and they would
uh moderate themselves up and they would
send their rivals down like the worst
would be like an embargoed news tech
release
uh where you know you got five p you got
your rs technicas and you got your pc
magazines and they've all got the same
embargo news story coming out at 1201
and they would all log in and moderate
their own story up and their
rival publications down and that would
just be like
you know a dozen people uh but it was
very much
i think at that that was kind of the era
where i realized oh great the
publications are just as crappy as the
randos
uh and uh it took me a little while to
realize that the governments would be
doing the exact same thing and that's
where we see our
the the twitters in the the mid-2015s or
the facebooks
uh where now you have government actors
doing
what uh what uh might have been being
done by a nand
tech or something in 2007. yeah
absolutely
and again this is what you should expect
game theory right
uh you give you give uh agents an
ecosystem and they will attempt to
manipulate it
you know i'll confess to in the early
days when i was i wouldn't call it the
early days of reddit the early days when
i was on reddit i had a dozen sock
puppets right
uh quite handy to kick your uh kick your
posts up a little bit particularly in
not so traffic
subreddits right you give yourself a
dozen upvotes over
six or seven hours and uh it definitely
helped of course people are going to do
that yeah
get uh your accounts to stop working on
slashdot yep exactly and so
we spent we spent years developing
defensive techniques against those sorts
of
uh those sorts of behaviors uh and i
actually felt a little bad for the
reddits and the digs because
uh when they started gaining traction uh
and popularity
those sorts of behaviors just became
immediately obvious and
the the users of those systems the
comment posters
had uh developed these techniques on
slashdot and we had spent years
hardening
ourselves against them uh so when uh the
when the next generation the web 2.0
generation came along
i felt bad because uh the the troll
population
uh was coming to the battle with machine
guns and they were they were defending
themselves with uh
you know two by fours and sticks
and they still are i mean frankly you
can you can still manipulate both reddit
and twitter fairly easily
although i would i would actually argue
that now
it seems like the people who are working
on the bots are are as much
me they're working with psychology uh as
much as anything else
they're they're they know what
stuff is gonna bite on people uh
and they're really careful about that i
think that uh
you know 15 years ago it was less about
the psychology and more about just
trying to make your point heard
uh and now it's a lot more savvy a lot
more
malicious i suppose yeah it's another
game that's opened up you know the old
the old game of upvoting still exists
brigading still exists i know a guy who
has an army of
trolls for instance right and he's real
active right now
manipulating things in the presidential
elections and so
uh yeah there's robot posting for sure
uh but good old brigading still exists
and you know it's a it's
as always an armed arms race platforms
are trying to detect it but hey you run
it through tours they don't know where
the hell you're coming from and you know
and you know but then they say all right
now people's ip's addresses are
evolving in a non-standard fashion that
ain't right so
then you start using ghost where you can
you know come out where you want
you know you're giving me flashbacks
because what you are basically
describing
was my day-to-day job from like 2000
till 2006
2007. oh great they figured out a new
way to
obfuscate their identity and slashdot at
its core we really worked hard
during my tenure to maintain the ability
to post anonymity here to post
anonymously
uh and that's not something i think that
exists anymore and i think that
i mean whether or not that's a that's a
value is a different discussion
uh but uh we valued it at the time
and that made it very difficult uh
for uh for us to have a lot of defenses
against folks because like you say tor
i mean even before tor um unsecured
relay servers that was our that was our
first problem on uh unsecured proxy
servers
uh and then that would evolve into tor
and then we had people
who would uh they would bought the
creation of user accounts
uh and uh so that they could get around
the
we would throttle anonymous users in in
you know maybe a little bit more rigidly
than regular users because i couldn't
tell if you were one user or 50
without enough data uh so we would i
don't know it
it was it was a difficult time uh and uh
it gave me a good sense of what the
folks that are at the major platforms
are dealing with today
and uh it's a bummer because they got
overwhelmed
uh and i think that now that everybody's
aware that that's a problem
uh it's it's a little bit too late the
cat's kinda out of the bag for those
folks
yeah sort of but you know nothing says
they couldn't change their moderations
uh policy well go ahead moderate
policies uh but uh it's it's
it's about uh user expectation uh
and i think that uh you but users of
these systems
uh like here's a dumb example
uh the fact that the the like count on
twitter is displayed as a numeric
integer creates a whole number of
perverse incentives for bad actors and
for good actors
but it but they can't take that number
away in 2020 people would freak
uh but you know that number is probably
damaging to them if they simply replaced
that with percentiles
and said this comments in the 99th
percentile for today
uh a lot of edge case behavior would go
away
uh but it also at the lower levels would
take away uh
incentive because uh moving to uh you
know the from the zero to the first
percentile is actually a pretty big
burden for
for most online content yep though
actually jack has mused about getting
rid of the count right he's
talked about it and at one point said he
was going to he didn't actually but
uh yeah they're at least thinking about
it right yeah
all the time uh i think that uh they're
all doing their best in a in a
questionable situation but
these decisions are hard and they have
influence uh
at the at the street level where you
just have like a random three people
tweeting back and forth at each other
but also at the the state actor level
uh these are hard hard problems and if
you haven't been deep in it uh
you don't understand the complexities of
them and you know
i wish them all the best uh i wish they
would have i wish they would have hired
me for like one day of consulting in
like 2008 so i could sit down with them
and say
look these are what this is what's going
to happen to you uh
you need to harden against this now you
know yep and
again they should have just known that
any ecosystem that has
targets of value that can be exploited
will be
exploited right and you discovered many
of them though probably not all of them
oh definitely
uh we were to start we were discovering
new ones right until the day left
yep uh is there anybody out there that's
using the
uh you know high value scarce uh
moderation technique that you guys had
yeah no i haven't seen well nobody's
using our specifics uh
i imagine there are systems out there
that that use them but they're probably
the notions that we're playing with
probably have more in common with video
games
than uh like a moderation system
you know things like running out of ammo
and stuff uh in a in a
in a in a game you know has a lot to do
with you know do we add more
ammo and more weapons to make this map
more fun or does that create this
make this map be uh imbalanced towards a
certain play style
i think that uh the gaming community
probably deals with these sorts of
problems
more uh than the reddit communities
because
i think that uh the the larger scale
systems
they're so focused on maximizing time on
site
uh that the notion that you would
throttle uh in interactive behavior
uh is is a difficult one because when
you i mean what what are you doing
except
uh designing metrics and measuring
success
with your various metrics uh and
what tells you that uh that a user is
enjoying your system more
than them clicking a like button that's
a big deal
uh and so they they they have a
different incentive
uh it's i don't know it's it's a it's a
hard problem uh i've never seen anybody
uh deploy things like at that to the
extreme scale that we did
there are plenty of systems that
restrict moderator access
but they generally do so to tiers or
classes of users
and not to uh i mean the slashdot system
was very much designed to give
everybody a shot uh like i i'm going to
test you out welcome to the system
you've been around for a couple of
months
i'm gonna test you out a couple of times
and if you prove yourself worthy
then you're gonna get to participate in
the system uh every couple of weeks and
if you don't then you're not gonna have
to play anymore
yeah great it was a great idea it really
was i and that's what that's actually
the conversation peter and i were having
said
hmm this was an actually interesting
different and at the time
seemingly effective uh way to do
moderation and we at least had never
seen it elsewhere
i think that uh i mean the the systems
today they suffer with uh with
another uh a number of uh interesting
hamstrings on this regard as well
uh one of slashdot's key advantages in
the early days is that the community was
really friggin smart
and the topic of the site was
relatively narrow uh it was all
generally tech or sci-fi or i mean it
was news for nerds it was it was that
that vain and especially for the first
few years
uh they're just we weren't talking about
uh
the general things that you would see
like on uh a national debate stage
uh we were talking about a niche uh and
so
if uh you're an expert uh in
operating systems uh then your your
opinion on uh
hardware and on video cards might be
reasonably accurate
uh but just because you're an expert in
encryption doesn't make you an expert in
immigration policy
uh and i think that the the modern
systems suffer from
uh you're you're expected to be all
things or people tend to be are
to per to portray themselves as being
expert in all things
when they're online so if i'm logged in
on reddit
uh or twitter uh whether or not i'm uh
uh participating in uh the uh
pc sales subreddit or
uh the donald i suppose the donald's not
around no more but uh
but but regardless the system regards me
as being generally equal
uh in each of these areas although i'm
maybe more of an expert
in one subject than the other uh and i
think that that's really where we end up
in so much trouble with the with the
twitter these days is that you have
a person who's an expert they have they
have a domain of expertise
and they gain followers because they
have a
domain expertise and then that allows
their ideas
outside of their expertise to be
weighed with uh an undeserved value
because of their expertise in another
domain uh and
so therefore because they were
successful in attracting followers
from their domain expertise area uh
their uh opinions on areas where they're
not they're simply not qualified
gain likes uh they gain they they gain
unearned popularity
uh and i think that a slashdot uh had a
lot of advantage because at least in the
earlier days the community was
relatively
focused uh on subject matter so we had
it we had a good advantage there as we
broadened out and
added things like politics and stuff to
the site i think that that that
uh became more of a problem uh but the
the modern systems they don't have
anything like that
uh on twitter you can follow me because
you're interested in seeing me make pens
you can follow me because you're
interested in uh
my podcast geeks in space or you can
follow me because you're interested in
my opinions on social media and modern
day use of moderation systems
but my
qualifications on any of these things
has nothing to do with the fact
my qualification for if i happen to
tweet that the detroit tigers won today
uh and obviously these are trivial
examples but people
use them for legitimately important
matters of discussion and the systems
don't seem to differentiate
between the two yep and you talk about
cross
leverage of expertise and of course on
twitter the even bigger problem is no
expertise you know so-called celebrities
you know they got
nine million followers and they mouth
off on all kinds of topics and they have
no expertise in anything they're just
famous for being well known the
definition of being a celebrity right
and that's the thing is that uh you know
the kanye west problem i suppose he may
very well be
an expert uh in something that he tweets
about
uh but he's famous for something else
and i have no way to vet his
uh credibility uh on a subject that
maybe he's never really actively
participated before and that's
that's sort of universally true you
shouldn't uh trust
my views on any political matter i have
no particular expertise in politics
my background is is generally technology
and social media
uh you shouldn't trust what i think
about i don't know immigration policy or
international relations i don't have any
but i might tweet about it
uh but if you're voting that up you know
it's not because i'm qualified
yep indeed that's a you know that's an
interesting
design issue if one were thinking about
how to do something like
social media correctly one of the things
you mentioned which i did not know at
the time was that you had
differential vote weights uh on slashdot
you know we were considering that in our
uh system in fact it was kind of a
stupid and naive
first attempt which we never actually
implemented but we'd specked out
making the up and down votes you'll love
this
weighted by the log five of your reddit
style karma how about that for an
obscure algorithm
it's not looney tunes uh we we did lots
of variations on that
uh so in the initial days of slashdot
scores the scores of comments were rated
from negative one to five and
the the the database entry was literally
just an integer
and it was literally just sum it all up
add and subtract when people
participated uh over time that became
uh not nearly com and not nearly good
enough because you have all sorts of
weird cases like for example
there's a difference between a comment
that's a score five and then somebody
tries to moderate it up to six
uh and then it so flutters five six five
six five six five six what does that
mean
uh to a user and to the moderators uh i
didn't i didn't like that because
i was trying to balance the number of
points being spent in the system on any
given day
uh but there's there's that's a signal
there and i have to capitalize on that
uh when we designed the achievement
system for slashdot
uh we sort of modeled it after the way
that world of warcraft did theirs but as
a joke
uh we made each of the tiers of um
of your rating of your achievement of
your score in the achievement system
uh each each was exponential it wasn't
log five it was exponential
so uh to you know get to rank eight
or whatever in an achievement category
it had to be two to the eighth
uh uh points uh or
uh events uh that measured that so
there were there were a number of uh
achievements in the system that uh
you know you'd suddenly find yourself
well you gotta post 16 million comments
in order to get to the next tier because
it's exponential
yeah log two base that's basically log
two right uh
and log five is even worse right right
and so we did we did
essentially a similar thing uh because i
didn't want people to treat that as a
gameable thing
so at some point uh the difference
between you know
if you're talking about uh like an easy
like a free action like a like or
something
on reddit um you know if a user has done
that
a hundred thousand times over the course
of a year whether or not they do it a
hundred thousand times or two hundred
thousand times doesn't really matter all
that much that you know the the
difference between you know that those
the orders of magnitude are really all
that matters at that point
that's exactly why we we like the log
the logarithmic scale because it does it
you know it's essentially the inverse
of the exponential so it's exactly that
reason you know the difference between a
hundred thousand
and two hundred thousand posts is much
more d
much different than between twenty posts
and a hundred thousand posts
right the the actual comment moderation
system on slashdot
uh didn't exactly use that uh
but uh we definitely like by the end we
had a lot
the system underneath is actually pretty
complicated when i left
uh and i can't imagine that it's changed
much
uh in the last eight nine years but uh
it's
uh there's a lot of weird math going on
underneath there
uh like to deal with like weird weird
edge cases like for example what happens
if i find a bot
uh in the system uh and uh i discover
that that bot has been doing something
crappy in my system for two weeks and i
didn't notice well
i the system that we had actually had
the ability to
extract that user from the system i
could erase their scores and that might
mean like a lot of weird stuff like the
example i was talking about earlier you
got a score five comment that gets
moderated up to six but slash that
doesn't have score six
so it's just four five four five four
five six five four five bouncing around
in that range
well what happens when you pull somebody
out uh
pull somebody's influence out of that
like i'm like a week later well that
comment isn't getting active moderation
uh so you actually have to replay uh the
moderation history
uh that occurred to that individual
comment and see that this guy
who uh you know you might have weighted
him as a 100 contributing user
uh a week ago but now you realize he's a
zero percent control you gotta you gotta
make sure that uh you keep the score
fair uh to the to the user who
uh posted the comment it's it's a it's
it's a hard problem
uh and i don't think people really think
through the complexities of this stuff
unless they are neck deep in it for a
few years
yeah and of course uh be even harder to
implement something like that on the
scale of uh
twitter or facebook where instead of you
know hundreds of thousands or a few
millions
of users you're talking about billions
right for sure and
they have the the further problem where
um
uh like like i was saying earlier you
know your post in one domain of
expertise
uh you could get retweeted tomorrow by
somebody who's
whose followers all exist within a
completely different domain of expertise
so a lot of your uh a lot of the
historical value
uh gets thrown out the window it's it's
it's a complicated problem
uh and i would absolutely uh i would
love
full access to those guys log files i'd
love to i'd love to
parse that data and see what's what's
going on have you ever reached out to
them to uh you know offer your expertise
and or get access to their data for
research purposes they do occasionally
give it out
uh i have uh academic friends who do
that sort of thing
uh but nobody at twitter or facebook
knows my name so it doesn't matter
yeah i had a guy philip howard on from
oxford who
leads the social media analysis uh
group over at oxford and they do uh
stuff like that and i
had on actually just last week rene
derista who
does something very similar at stanford
uh you know if you'd like to be
introduced to those folks i'd be happy
to do it yeah you should uh you might
want to talk to cliff lampe at
uh university of michigan he does a lot
of that stuff too
sounds good so let's finish the story uh
what happened this what happened with
slash dot
uh why did hacker news kick your ass
uh hacker news never kicked our ass
hacker news is a different deal entirely
um well i think slashdot
became victim of his own success uh
we uh that when the site began
it was a very dedicated population of
contributors uh who were generally
expert
uh in the the areas of the nerd culture
that we were doing
that we were covering and uh over the
years
uh other choices came along and
uh when a population starts off with a
core of experts
the inevitable thing that happens is
that a secondary population of
of hangers on uh
moves into the into the system as well
and
uh i think that uh over the course of a
few years
uh a lot of the expert folks got pretty
annoyed by the noobs
uh and other possibilities came out too
uh
what happens like reddit and twitter uh
and i guess before before those to a
certain extent dig
uh they they created a different kind of
incentive for users because the story
selection process
that those platforms used was
driven entirely or mostly entirely by
the the
the users themselves which meant that
those systems can be faster
a tweet that i make right now goes out
to all of my followers within a second
uh and they are limited only by how fast
they can refresh or how often they
refresh twitter on any given day
slash dot had itself limited to you know
let's say a dozen
a dozen articles a day a dozen stories a
day so
if you want more than 12 stories a day
or if you
are more interested and you want to deep
dive into a specific area well that's
not going to work too well for you on
slashdot
so the the the reddits and the twitters
allowed the power user to get more of
what they wanted
and it allowed them to get it faster
and once the power users started
figuring that out well the power users
started losing interest
uh in slashdot because at that point
they have to jump through the
editorial hoop created by the slashdot
editorial process itself
uh and that's that's legit and fair and
i i would do the same in their shoes
most likely
uh but uh i think that uh you play that
forward for a few years and you lose
five ten fifteen twenty percent of your
original audience uh for that reason and
then what you have left is a
is a bit of a hollow shell compared to
what you had before
so it wasn't so much uh a collapse as
much as it was a slow sad death by
attrition
um and uh i i don't think that hacker
news
kicked our butt uh i would actually say
that uh
dig knocked us off our pedestal uh
reddit did it did it mostly right uh
twitter's a different beast
uh i mean twitter and reddit and
facebook are i guess the dominant
platforms now and
they each succeed and fail along a very
specific
vector but they each have very clear
advantages
out of uh over slash dot even without
talking about the
the the scale advantages that you have
uh because the other thing to keep in
mind is that with slashdot i
very very consciously worked my butt off
to
keep it uh within a very specific
sphere of of domain expertise i didn't
want slashdot covering stuff that was
outside of the news for nurse nerds
umbrella
and if you want something that's not the
news in under the news for nerds
umbrella you gotta go somewhere else
and i think that uh that was slashdot's
advantage but that had the uh the
negative side effect that
anybody who's going to be reading
slashdot in 2008
was probably reading slashdot in 1990 98
and the thing about people is that we
can't make more people that were reading
slashdot in 1998 that's a fixed pool
that can only shrink
uh so the only way that you can grow
your population is to broaden
uh your domain of expertise uh or lower
your standards
and i wasn't really comfortable with
either of those options
and i don't know what's happening over
there today but i imagine probably more
of the same
interesting well rob thank you very much
for
a walk through the history of one of the
more important
uh web sites of that era
uh i was particularly enjoyed uh jumping
into more of the details on how your
comment moderation system worked and
i hope some listeners out there who work
at some of these platform companies or
have influence on them
might say hey maybe they ought to talk
to this guy rob right he's uh he's been
through this before it may not be
directly applicable but
some of this thinking i suspect would
help these platform companies do a
better job on what they're trying to do
today
i mean i don't mean to brag but i pretty
much think i'm the world's greatest
uh and that they should all be paying me
as a highly paid consultant on
all of these matters uh i mean but i
might have some biases
yeah it's just possible just like i
think my granddaughter's got to be the
most beautiful baby in the world right
i i have no reason to believe otherwise
all righty so if you want to
catch up on what rob's thinking or at
least babbling about you can catch him
up on
geeks and space podcast available on
your favorite podcast app i'm imagining
probably i honestly don't know i've
never heard it
yeah frankly i won't tell you how many
times i was into my podcast but ain't
many
uh anyway thanks rob and this was fun
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com